<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A faithful testimony for God &amp; my country, or, A retro-spective glass for the legislators and the rest of the sons of the Church of England (so called), who are found persecuting the innocent</title>
            <author>Billing, Edward, 1623-1686.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1664</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 27 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A28151</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B2900</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6254</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12320785</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12320785</idno>
            <idno type="VID">59472</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A28151)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59472)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 203:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A faithful testimony for God &amp; my country, or, A retro-spective glass for the legislators and the rest of the sons of the Church of England (so called), who are found persecuting the innocent</title>
                  <author>Billing, Edward, 1623-1686.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1664.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Edward Billing. Cf. Halkett &amp; Laing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Harvard University Libraries.</note>
                  <note>Signed: E.B.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:59472:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A FAITHFUL TESTIMONY FOR God &amp; my Country: OR, A Retro-ſpective Glaſs FOR THE LEGISLATORS, And the reſt of the SONS OF THE Church of England, (So called) Who are found Perſecuting the INNOCENT.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for the Author, in the Year, 1664.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:59472:2"/>
            <head>A faithful Testimony for God and my Country, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>FRiends, had you by the greatneſs of your Valor invaded, and <hi>Vi &amp; Armis</hi> conquered the Nation, or were they your ſubdued Vaſſals through the puiſſance of your Courage, whom you now pretend to ſell for ſlaves, You had then had the Rigidity of Infidels for your Parallel: But for you who were <hi>amicably</hi> admitted into Truſt and Government, to ſo much as offer to baniſh, or ſell for ſlaves the free-born Denizens of <hi>England,</hi> becauſe they are Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally-minded, and for Conſcience-ſake cannot conform to the Carnal Ordinances of man, contrary to the Royal Law of God written in their hearts; I ſay, if this be not utterly below the Heroick Spirit of all Generoſity as well as Chriſtianity, let the holy Witneſs of God in all Conſciences judge.</p>
            <p>But alas, poor mortals! what have you undertaken? Ye are as ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable to divert the courſe of the Sun, or impede the flux and reflux of the Seas, as ye are to ſtop the ſpreading, conquering and flouriſhing growth of the Truth and Goſpel of our Lord <hi>Jeſus;</hi> for infinitely greater is HE that is in Us, than the God of the men of your World: wherefore in vain do you think through your unnatural coercion, to cauſe us to forſake GOD the Living Fountain (who hath never failed us) to drink of your lifeleſs puddles, or ſo much as deign to taſt of thoſe Husks, which you call Bread; I tell you, Nay, for we know better things; and our Rock is as invincible, our Armour in the Light as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penetrable, and our Fountain as precious and inexhauſtible as when firſt we believed; and the holy Religion that we through the Light of <hi>Jeſus</hi> in the Conſcience do already conform to, and live in, is not of yeſterday, as the ignorant moſt vainly imagine, nor the Principle leading thereto ſubject to change, or liable to expulſion; neither may we in the exerciſe thereof run ſhirking into holes, or skulk into cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners by <hi>threes</hi> or <hi>fours,</hi> as the <hi>now Peſtiferous Locuſts</hi> did a few years ſince, when the Powers of the Earth bid them be ſilent or took away their fleece: For through the Grace and Mercy which is infinit, we
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:59472:3"/> know and have believed in the Living God, and <hi>Jeſus</hi> THE Chriſt, whom he hath ſent to <hi>redeem</hi> and <hi>ſave his People from,</hi> not <hi>in</hi> their <hi>ſins:</hi> And we have eaten (eternal thanks be to his holy Name) of that Fleſh, and drank of that Blood which admits not of hunger or thirſt after the Inventions or Traditions of man any more; and ſuch knowing the immortal Truth through the Revelation of the Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Goſpel (for which they have an infallible Teſtimony to bear) cannot fly, although your Furnace were or ſhould be made ſeven times hotter than it already is. Nay, nay; for our deſcent is legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timated by the Generator of the Juſt, and the Birth of our day is more Noble, our Principle and Spirit more publick and true than ſo; and our mouths were not opened by, neither can they be ſhut in the will of man; inſomuch, that what we receive in ſecret, that declare we openly and freely among you, for it admits of no limitation, neither fear we the gainſaying <hi>Jews</hi> of this Age; and if our Goſpel and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Teſtimony be hid from any <hi>[in this the Lord's Day]</hi> it's onely from ſuch who periſh through their own oppoſition or oppoſing the Light in themſelves and others; for the Candle-Royal, the Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Light of the Living-God, which is lighted, brought forth and ſet up, in and among the Land of the Living, cannot, is not whelmed under a buſhel, nor can the prevalent in-flaming power thereof be extinguiſhed by any humane Law.</p>
            <p>And your ſelves cannot rationally think by this your unnatural Act (the effect whereof is, let a million be concerned, and an hundred thouſand periſh, rather than the inordinate wills of a very few be croſſed) to ſo much as influence or endear any ſober man in the Nations: and for Converts you need not expect one; ſome few ye may divert through hypocriſie into further deceit, who with their Bodies for ſlaviſh fear or diſhoneſt gain, may conform, and ye may alſo therewith gratifie the Prophane, and cauſe the Seed of Evil-doers for a ſeaſon to rejoyce: But O! the Cryes and Prayers of the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, with the Tears and Groans of the Captives, the Widdows and Fatherleſs will further prevail than many Armies of that uncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed Leaven.</p>
            <p>But there are ſome ſo impudent to alledge that this your Act is not againſt Conſcience, (but it's like they are ſuch who have made ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack of their own that thus babble) however the indelible characters written with the effuſed blood of the Innocent and truly Conſcienci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:59472:3"/> (which will never ceaſe to cry) have by woful experience mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted all ſuch Allegations to be <hi>fictitious</hi> and <hi>a lye;</hi> wherefore in vain doth the Serpent go about to <hi>Hide</hi> himſelf there. Indeed the Tail of the Dragon is not the Head of the Serpent, neither are his Teeth and Tayl his Cloven-feet: for have you not a Law that would compell us to your Worſhip? and another that excommunicates us becauſe we do not come? Is there not a third of the ſame ſpecies, that robs and impriſons us for Antichriſtian-Tythes? and a fourth that would likewiſe compel us, againſt a poſitive Command of Chriſt, to ſwear; and is there not a fifth and ſixth, in caſe of refuſal, that <hi>praemunires</hi> and requires us upon pain of death to abjure the Land? Interweave with the ſweep of this Drag, that of your own making, prohibiting our Meetings, and requiring us alſo to ſwear upon pain of being ſold for Bondſlaves<note n="†" place="margin">For who can be ſo inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious to his own reaſon, to pay for his being tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt his own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; and then the words of your Act (ſo far as I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member) are, <hi>The She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riff may diſtrain, and for want of diſtreſs he hath power to contract with any Merchant, &amp;c.</hi> that is, he hath power to ſell me for ſeven years.</note>; and if It, with the reſt, make not up a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat Labyrinth of Thraldomes againſt Conſcience, then judge thou O Righteous Judge of Heaven and Earth!</p>
            <p>Is this the Indulgence ſo often promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to tender Conſciences? and did not the King ſay in his late Declaration, That he was an Enemy in his nature to Sangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary and Capital Puniſhments? If to Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh an <hi>Innocent</hi> man from his Wife, or a <hi>tender</hi> mother from her <hi>innocent</hi> babes and husband, be not capital or ſanguinary pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment; Nay, if it be not the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite of Cruelties, judge thou O Lord my God, for thy Judgments are, and will be juſt, and thy Decrees are righteous altogether, and in thy ſeaſon ſhall moſt ſurely be fulfilled, although at the preſent thy Enemies rage, and the Rulers in the Earth decree the Baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thine Anointed forth of their Land.</p>
            <p>When firſt I heard that ſuch a <hi>Bill</hi> was preparing to be offered in <hi>Parliament,</hi> I ſaid in my heart, Can, Dare, or will any, called <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhmen,</hi> give their conſent to the paſſing thereof? How! the Peoples Repreſentatives in <hi>Parliament</hi> give their conſents to puniſh the moſt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:59472:4"/> innocent Natives with no leſs than Baniſhment, and upon their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn with Death, for the exerciſe of their pure Conſciences to God!</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>To Death ſuch immane Crueltyes, I ſhall decry,</l>
                  <l>And with my Blood I'le freely ſeal,</l>
                  <l>Your Act's againſt the Commonweal.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Alſo know all the Actors, by your Act unminded,</l>
                  <l>That it's no Law till <hi>Magna Charta</hi> be reſcinded,</l>
                  <l>Though with't you do and may the Innocent vex,</l>
                  <l>Not minding <hi>SALUS POPULI SUPREMA LEX.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>Well, if it were poſſible for you to obtain your wills, and that you could rid out of the Nation all ſuch who for Conſcience ſake, in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to Chriſt's Command, cannot ſwear, nor, as moved by his holy Spirit, forbear to meet often together, to <hi>wait upon and ſerve the Lord;</hi> neither Conform to your Church-Worſhip (And what man that ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly feareth God in any meaſure, doth not ſome of your Laws againſt Conſcience reach?) Who ſhould then Plow the Earth, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the Induſtry now uſed therein? It's not Prophaneſs, Drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enneſs, Oaths, Lyes, Luſt and Perſecution, and ſuch who nouriſh their hearts in the Senſuality of all manner of Uncleanneſſes, (though Sons of your Church) that will be long able to give to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> or put into the <hi>Hirelings</hi> mouths; and then to be ſure, if they are not very much degenerated from their old nature, they'l prepare War and contrive Inſurrections, the prevention whereof, is the alledged pretention why this your <hi>Act of Prevention</hi> was paſſed againſt the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent</hi> [but it is more then palpable, it's the exerciſe of our holy Conſcience to God that is ſtruck at: For if really and alone to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent Inſurrections, was the Cauſe why the <hi>Act</hi> was paſſed, what's the reaſon that Women, and Men paſt ſixty, or otherwiſe impotent were not excepted?] But to cut ſhort all ſuch pretention; I tell you plainly, it's time enough for an <hi>Engliſh-man</hi> to be impeached when really <hi>guilty,</hi> and to ſuffer when matter of Fact is fully and le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally proven. I am ſure that's the hereditary undoubted Right, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutly due to the meaneſt perſon born within the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation. And that good <hi>Cilician, Paul,</hi> being enſnared for the exerciſe of his
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:59472:4"/> pure Conſcience, as at this day we are, Pleaded the Priviledge of the Nation and City whereof he was; and thoſe generous <hi>Heathens, Claudius Licius, Felix, Feſtus</hi> and <hi>Agrippa</hi> did not deny him his Birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, but like men of noble minds, permitted him to ſpeak for himſelf to the full; ingenuouſly admitting his Appeal unto <hi>Caeſar,</hi> who though a profeſſed <hi>Heathen,</hi> ſuffered <hi>Paul,</hi> a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> not only to live, but alſo to preach Chriſtianity in <hi>Rome,</hi> no man moleſting him; ſo that, that great Emperour did not imploy his Souldiers (like Brutes) to pull <hi>Paul</hi> and his Friends out of his Houſe, and break up their Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, though it's moſt probable he had oft-times with him an hundred times <hi>four,</hi> beſides them of his Family; and yet it was not ignorantly call'd, <hi>A Seditious Conventicle, &amp;c.</hi> But the accurſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>High Prieſt</hi> of the <hi>Jews</hi> who read the Law, as your <hi>Prieſts</hi> do the Prayers that you call <hi>Common,</hi> and talked of the <hi>Meſſia</hi> to come, as yours do of <hi>Chriſt</hi> now he is come, inſinuating with the Rulers of the Earth then, as at this day, being aſſiſted with the baſer ſort then, as now, ſuffered <hi>Paul</hi> to be ſmitten and abuſed contrary to the Law, as at this day we are: And was it not the <hi>Hirarchy</hi> then, who ſent their Armed <hi>Mercenaries,</hi> Satans <hi>Vaſſals,</hi> with <hi>their</hi> ſuborned <hi>Judas,</hi> to ſeize upon, and hale the <hi>Innocent Lamb of God</hi> before their Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Seat, or pretended <hi>Spiritual Court;</hi> where, by a Law incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinently, they condemned the <hi>Saviour of the World,</hi> prevailing (through their ſubtilty) with <hi>Pilate</hi> [even againſt the Witneſs of God in his conſcience] to give up Jeſus the <hi>Juſt One,</hi> to the Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifiction, (in whom he found no <hi>fault</hi>) and deliver to them and their accomplices <hi>Barrabas</hi> a Murderer; and <hi>Pilate</hi> having once drank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Preiſts Sorceries, fell below the ſtate of a man, permitting his Souldiers to <hi>Spit</hi> in his Saviours face, <hi>Crown him with Thorns, Strike, Mock</hi> and <hi>Revile</hi> him on the Croſs, give him <hi>Gall</hi> and <hi>Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar to drink,</hi> caſt <hi>Lots</hi> for his Garments, receive the Prieſts Bribery to <hi>lye;</hi> all which was as far beneath the Nobility of the <hi>Romans,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Prieſts ſpirit had entered them, as our Uſage at this day is beneath the ſpirit of True <hi>Engliſh-men,</hi> and contrary to the Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Laws of the Land whereof we are <hi>Free-born.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For in the firſt place, We are not only illegally ſeized upon, Drag'd through your Streets and Canels, knock'd down, Hair and Garments rent off, Blood drawn, bruiſed and beaten to exceſs, even
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:59472:5"/> ſeveral to death, and many other moſt ſordid immanities (againſt Law) done unto us (which a large Volumn will not contain) but as illegally ſent to Priſon; and when Priſoners, and brought before Judicatories (ſo called) denied to be heard; our mouths ſtopp'd at the Judges command, by the hand of the Common Hangman and other aſſiſtant miſcrants, with Gags, and by thruſting naſty hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kirchifs, rouled up, into the months of the <hi>Innocent</hi> ready to ſufficate them; alſo ſtriking of them many dreadful Blows with great Canes or Cudgels (at leaſt a hundred) upon their bare heads and other parts of their bodies, and this by command, and at the <hi>Bar of Juſtice</hi> (ſo called) and for no other Cauſe but legally pleading for their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties and Eſtates, having been a conſiderable time falſly impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and ought by the Law of the Land, at leaſt to have been freed, nought being found or proven againſt them. But inſtead of recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving any manner of Juſtice, moſt rediculouſly and impertinantly was the <hi>Oath of Allegiance,</hi> impoſed as a Snare upon them; for refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal whereof they were forthwith <hi>premunired,</hi> and their Eſtates and Liberties in this horrid manner rap'd from them.</p>
            <p>As likewiſe ſince, at the ſame place, to wit, the Seſſions-houſe in the <hi>Old-Bailey London,</hi> about forty Friends were brought from <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate</hi> thither, and ſet to the Bar; a falſe Indictment read againſt ſome few of them, and for faſhion-ſake a Jury impannell'd; ſome Witneſs, ſuch as it was, but not being ſufficient to prove the Indictment, the purport whereof was, <hi>For being at an Unlawful Aſſembly, Seditious Meeting, Conventicle, or Worſhip, contrary to the Lyturgy of the Church of England,</hi> or ſuch ſtuff ſo far as I remember. After twice going out, the Jury brought in their Verdict, <hi>That the Priſoners were not guilty of any Seditious Conventicle, Unlawful Aſſembly,</hi> or the like. Whereupon they were exceedingly menaced, furiouſly interrogated, their Verdict by the Judge (ſo called) refuſed, and by him ſix of them bound-over to anſwer it at the <hi>Kings-Bench Bar;</hi> and all this, becauſe they could not without ſufficient Witneſs, contrary to their Conſcience, finde the Innocent <hi>Guilty.</hi> Are not the Jury Judges of matter of Fact (at leaſt) and to give their Verdict according to their Conſcience and Judgment? and is not the Judge obliged to receive the Juries Verdict, and acquit the Priſoner, or give Judgment ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly<note n="*" place="margin">See one of your own Preſidents in that caſe, the ſubſtance whereof is this, ſo far as I remember; <hi>(viz.)</hi> An Innocent man was indicted for Felony; the Witneſſes ſwearing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, the Jury brought him in Guilty; and notwithſtanding the Judge himſelf knew the man in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted was innocent, and likewiſe, knew the perſon that did the Felony, yet he was forced to paſs Sentence upon the Innocent, becauſe the Jury had brought him in guilty; and all the Judge could do was, to reprieve him until he had got his Pardon from the King.</note>:
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:59472:5"/> But theſe Innocents were remanded to Priſon (though cleared by the Jury) and there to remain. This is not all, (although ſo abominable, that I do believe the like hath not been done in <hi>England</hi> in any Judicatory this many hundred years) but two dayes after, twenty Friends (or there-abouts) Men and Women, were at the place aforeſaid, upon the authority of <hi>ſic volo ſic jubeo,</hi> ſentenſed to Baniſhment without any Jury at all, or being legally heard, notwithſtanding they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver refuſed, according to their underſtandings and a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, to plead the general Iſſue, the which with one voice they then affirmed to the Iudge in the face of the Court; (ſo called) though it be moſt evident (by the <hi>London Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> uſage) that pleading or not pleading, Iury or no Iury, is much at one. As was alſo ſomewhat manifeſted at <hi>Hicks's Hall</hi> the ſame week, where the Grand Iury, at their firſt and ſecond going forth, could not find the Bill; but being check'd and threatned to be fined, at their third going forth (the Clerk of the Peace going up to help them) it was ſaid the Bill was found; I ſay, it was alledged it was found, but it was not clear to many (if any) of the by-ſtanders. How ever, with ſuch Witneſs and Petty-Jury as they were, there were likewiſe ſentenced to Baniſhment Twelve Innocents, to any of the Kings Plantations, <hi>Virginia</hi> and <hi>Barbados</hi> excepted: but one of the Juſtices (ſo called) informed the Judge that <hi>Virginia</hi> was one of the places excepted in the Act; then he mentioned <hi>Hiſpaniola,</hi> (a place that never yet belonged to <hi>England</hi>) and one that ſtood by and heard him, ſaid, <hi>Oliver did not get that for you;</hi> ſo that at that time he did not condeſcend upon any particular place. Indeed the man was greatly confounded, inſomuch that his lips trembled exceedingly when he pronounced his confuſed Sentence, which to me was an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>falible ſign that God's hand was againſt him.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:59472:6"/>
            <p>As for the illegal, abſurd and cruel proceedings laſt <hi>Aſſizes</hi> and <hi>Quarter-Seſſion</hi> holden at <hi>Hertford,</hi> where by Baniſhing twenty nine innocent true Men from their dear Wives and tender innocent Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren (ſixteen of them being married, and ſeveral of them alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſhipt) hath on your part, and by vertue of the Authority deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from you, in effect made ſixteen Widows, and at leaſt fourty or fifty Fatherleſs Children; the which being already <hi>malafama</hi> through and through the Nation, I ſhall but only mention it, and as dung, amongſt the reſt of the precited inhumane Violences, ſpread it before you; that ſo you may plainly ſee, if prejudice utterly blind not, how we are really enſlaved, and contrary to <hi>Magna Charta</hi> and the moſt wholſome Laws of the Land, deſtroyed in our Lives, Liberties and Eſtates, even by the power that is derived from your late Act. Since the unnatural birth whereof (where the Magiſtrates through God's Mercy to them and us have not been reſtrain'd) have not our Perſons been impriſon'd, and our innocent Blood drank as freely as other cups of Vice and Pleaſure? Not leſs than the bodies of twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſeven precious Souls deſtroyed, in and through Cruel Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in <hi>Newgate,</hi> ſince your Act became in force; being taken, and Impriſoned to death, only for worſhipping the <hi>Lord their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker</hi> in the Spirit and in the Truth. Is not this <hi>turning</hi> of Juſtice <hi>backward,</hi> and Equity into <hi>Cruelty?</hi> makes not ſuch doings your Thrones of Juſtice (ſo called) to become Stages of <hi>Infamy,</hi> and your moſt legal Theaters moſt artificial <hi>Aceldama's?</hi> and think ye that the Living God of Heaven and of Earth will not viſit for theſe things, and make a dreadful inquiſition for the Blood and Sufferings of his <hi>Innocent Seed? YEA, YEA, YEA,</hi> as ſure as he is God; and its more requiſite for you, to expect the revelation of his Indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, than daily Bread. <hi>What can I ſay?</hi> You will as ſurely feel his Juſtice, as ever you ſaw his Mercy; and your whole Arm of Fleſh ſhall be no more able to deliver you from his Vengeance, than one ſingle Reed; wherefore, in vain do you fight againſt God in his <hi>Seed,</hi> or go about to limit his <hi>Holy Ones</hi> in the exerciſe of their holy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, to your <hi>way,</hi> or <hi>number.</hi> Had not Chriſt twelve Apoſtles, and did the ignoble <hi>Jews</hi> go about to reſtrict him to the number of <hi>five?</hi> and were not oft-times ſeveral hundreds, and ſometimes thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands conveen'd to hear him and them preach? though indeed they were, as we now are, by the ſame <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> and <hi>Hierarchical</hi>-ſpirit
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:59472:6"/> caſt out as Evil-Doers, thought not worthy to live; comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to ſpeak <hi>no more in that Name;</hi> called <hi>Sowers of Sedition, Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Fellows, Ring-Leaders of Sects, Perverters of the Laws, Turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the World upſide down, &amp;c.</hi> However, theſe our Primitive Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors fearing and obeying God, rather than man, met often to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, ſometimes <hi>in the Field,</hi> ſometimes <hi>by the Sea-ſide,</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <hi>at one Friends houſe,</hi> and ſometimes at another, or the like. And did not the Apoſtle incite the True Chriſtians, <hi>to meet often to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,</hi> and rebuke ſuch <hi>who forſook the Aſſemblies of the Saints?</hi> wherefore ſome grew <hi>weak,</hi> and others fell <hi>aſleep.</hi> And whether do you think its juſter before God, for us to obey the Spirit of Chriſt <hi>in Us,</hi> and follow the bleſſed Example of him and his holy Apoſtles, or your Edict? And was <hi>Daniel</hi> a Rebel, when he brake the Decree of <hi>Darius,</hi> King of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi> whoſe Statutes are ſaid to be <hi>unalterable?</hi> Yet holy <hi>Daniel</hi> valued not the <hi>anti-conſcience</hi> Law of the King his Maſter (whoſe immediate Servant he was) but boldly opened his windows, and prayed to his God as at other times. And for my part, I tell you plainly, I purpoſe in my heart, all the dayes of my life to wait upon, and pray to my God, as at other times, as holy <hi>Daniel</hi> did, notwithſtanding your Decree to the contrary; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly knowing, my God can deliver me if he pleaſe: but as to mine own part, whether my dayes ſhall be many, or few, my death publick or private, <hi>O Lord, thou knoweſt I am not at all anxious or careful in that matter.</hi> And as I would not be profuſe of my Blood, even ſo I abhor the very thought of being nigardly of my life, for the further Teſtimony of the Goſpel and immortal Truth, as it is holden forth and diſpenſ'd, by thoſe depicable, yet <hi>precious Ones,</hi> (who trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at his Word) in ſcorn called <hi>Quakers.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Wherefore thy Will, not mine be done, O God moſt Wiſe.</l>
               <l>Chriſt's Croſs I love; the Pain, the Shame, I utterly deſpiſe.</l>
               <l>Your Baniſhment, your Goal and Gibbet I defie;</l>
               <l>When you are ready ſo am I, for God and's Truth to die.</l>
            </q>
            <p>However, it had been but reaſonable among men, before you had paſſed a Decree to Impriſon, Fine, Baniſh, ſell for Slaves, and upon their Return, to put to Death ſo conſiderable a part of the Nation, as we (and others concerned in your late Act) are, to have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veen'd
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:59472:7"/> a ſufficient number of your Prieſts (for whom you thus drudg) and Us together, and your ſelves have heard if they could have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced us, that we held or declared any thing for Doctrine or Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion derogatory to God, or Chriſt Jeſus the Light of the World; or that we had <hi>preached for Hire,</hi> or <hi>divined for Money, handfuls of Corn</hi> or <hi>pieces of Bread,</hi> (as the falſe Prophets did and do) or if they could have plainly evinced to you, we had like Belly-gods, idle Drones, greedy Dumb-dogs who can never have enough, robb'd the Nation of the <hi>Tenth,</hi> or <hi>ſeventh part</hi> of their Eſtates and yearly induſtry, then it had been time to have cryed <hi>Away with them:</hi> for ſuch men, as ſuch, are indeed pernitious to the Publick-weal, a burden and a plague to our Nation.</p>
            <p>Or rather, in the firſt place, immediatly after God had permitted you into outward Power and Government, It had been fitter for you to have put on ſackcloth and aſhes, and in humility of ſoul have turned <hi>inward,</hi> and waited <hi>there</hi> in brokenneſs of heart, at <hi>Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms gate,</hi> that ſo ye might have come to have felt and known what the Lord had meant (conſidering what bad men you had been) to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voul ſuch undeſerved Truſt and Power upon you. But alas, alas, inſtead of doing thus, have ye not turned the Grace of God into Wantonneſs, Pride, Oaths, Perſecution, and many other unutterable Abominations<note n="*" place="margin">Him that's free I neither interrogate, nor accuſe, although I expect he that's moſt guilty ſhould be ready to throw the firſt ſtone at me.</note>? And can you expect ought but a ſutable reward, and that God ſhould make a dreadful deciſion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Juſt and the Unjuſt, betwixt them who ſerve him, and them who will not ſerve him themſelves, nor ſuffer others? Indeed, were I ſo vicious as very very many of the ſons of your Church are, I ſhould rather expect the eternal Vengeance of the dreadful God forthwith to ſweep me from the face of the Earth, than his intolerably provoked Mercy ſhould permit me to live one day longer to blaſpheam. And truly, friends, the <hi>Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monger, Swearer, Lyar, Drunkard, Adulterer</hi> and <hi>Idolatrous, Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor</hi> be you aſſured God will ſeverely judge; and <hi>the Thirſters af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Blood of the Innocent ſhall not live out half their dayes,</hi> and <hi>the Memorial of the Wicked ſhall Rot.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>E. B.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
